this is the best insurance law podcast
brought to you by best recommended
insurance attorneys welcome to best
insurance law podcast the broadcast
about timely and important legal issues
affecting the insurance industry I'm
John Zimmer managing editor vests
recommended insurance attorneys
including expert service providers
please have with us today trip Wagner
from expert service provider Jensen
Hughes Jensen Hughes is a global leader
in safety security and risk-based
engineering and consulting since 1939
Tripp is a senior forensic mechanical
engineer located out of West Chester
Pennsylvania he conducts forensic
investigations in origin and cause on
fire losses fire suppression systems and
on fire related losses he has been
involved in the forensic evaluation or
cause of 1,200 fire losses chip has also
testified in approximately 80 cases as
an expert in fire related cases and is a
retired Delaware State Deputy Fire
Marshal Tripp thank you so much for
joining us this morning thank you for
having me on John today's discussion is
on how claims handling and inspections
have changed in scope of 19 and Tripp
for our first question today how has
Kovac 19 impacted forensic engineering
claims handling and relationship with
insurers so as a whole during all this a
process has slowed down and that begins
with retaining information from the
insured reaching the insured scheduling
inspections the time it is taking to
travel to inspections and complete
inspections we have a delay now and
parties receiving notice you know just
errs attorneys corporations everybody is
working from home certified letters may
not be going through as they usually do
so we've slowed down on the receiving
notice and replying and and we've also
seen a delay in joint exams being
scheduled there's a lot of travel issues
there's a lot of scheduling issues so we
have the delay all the way to the joint
exams and it continues through the whole
process all the way to lab exam so the
biggest thing we're seeing is a slowdown
in everything everything is kind of hit
the brakes the first thing that happened
when
we encountered this current environment
we are in is in the forensic world we
saw product reps losing the ability to
travel and when I speak about product
reps I'm mostly referring to internal
experts from corporations or companies
so if you were to take a major auto
manufacturer when there's a loss
whatever type of loss it may be they
prefer to send their internal experts
and not hire an outside company and
those were the first people we saw that
would reach back and say we're shut down
we're not allowed to travel and that's
understandable because they are not
forensic firms they are large
corporations and just as a corporation
they said no more travel so that was the
first issue we came across what that
ended up resulting in is we saw some
expert selection change so everybody has
their favored expert and everybody has
the expert they prefer the these
corporations would like their internal
experts conversely product manufacturers
may like a certain expert that has to
travel across the country and what we
saw was that's not doable sometimes
there there are many limitations it may
not just be the company that's saying
that it may be the individual it may be
just the inability to get to a location
so we saw companies having to think
outside the box and maybe work with a
local expert and they work with their
preferred expert and work in cooperation
but we definitely saw a selection change
and we had to move forward many times so
you have to work outside the box and
work together as all parties to get that
accomplished and and lastly one of the
big things is we saw the the lack of
ability to interface with the insured
the insured when it comes to a loss no
matter what type of loss are a huge
avenue of data to gather right there the
first one may be to discover the loss
they have history with the appliance the
plumbing whatever it may be and we lost
the ability to have them come out to our
site you know pre kovat we would have in
an ideal world we'd have the insured
show up we'd walk through and look at
items and say what was this when did we
do this that's gone you know the insured
generally is not willing to meet with
experts and it's understandable in our
environment so they are no longer there
and we have lost on an
this amount of data that we usually
could gain as a result of that trip how
our scene inspections being handled now
so scene inspections are definitely
handled differently and I think we are
going to see them handle differently
throughout the future I don't think this
is just going to stop anytime soon the
biggest thing about seeing exams is what
type of scene exams do we have and
simplistically we may say like a
business versus a residential so
residential scene exams are having
changed immensely and especially if the
residence is still occupied and what
comes to mind for me as an example of a
loss we had which was a chimney fire
when this first started but it did not
destroy the house it was still occupied
so we had to discuss with the insured we
need to proceed with this we need to get
into your home to examine this what are
you comfortable with conversely what am
i comfortable with as the expert you
know what is going on in the home what
PPE would we have to wear there's an
enormous amount of exchange of
information that has to go on upfront
prior to even the initial exam and this
is just the first party going out we're
not even talking about the joint we're
talking about maybe the first fire
investigator the first engineer going
out whatever maybe it needs to be
discussed upfront need to determine what
can happen what needs to be done to
proceed with the inspection and then you
need to make sure all those things are
accomplished in that case the insured
was okay with us coming in with Tyvek
respirator gloves limiting our amount of
time in there and doing what we needed
to do on the initial inspection to
gather the information we need to gather
now that exam proceeded to a joint exam
so now we're at the point where okay now
we have luckily it wasn't a large exam
and this is just one example there's
many like this but we had four parties
and we had to discuss with everybody up
front including the insured again
you know we are going to limit the
amount of people that are allowed inside
the home if your attorney is going to be
present one party is going to be allowed
inside the home and this is the PPE that
we are going to need to wear to move
forward and I can understand that from
both the insured and
the expert side and I think that's gonna
go on for a while it also did limit a
little bit it can limit what data you
can gain you can have an insured saying
no you can have an insurance a I will
let one person down to my basement to
view this fireplace and when you get to
that point of a joint exam you have to
be cooperative with all the other
experts no matter what side you are to
say look guys only one person can get
down there I'm going to document as much
information as I can and I will share
with all parties you need to tell me
what you want what you want to see and
we'll go from there and I've also had
the other side I had a small water loss
where the insurance company reached out
to me and said look I've spoken with the
insured they have an infant they're
going to retain everything and we are
going to send you out there in July or
August when this is done and that
required a call to the insurer to
discuss with them to make sure they
retain everything appropriately and they
moved everything needed into their
basement and will follow up in July so
that's the residential side which are an
enormous amount of losses the other side
you have is a business and obviously we
have many more industrial I'm just going
to grab the two most common and the
short time we have to discuss this this
environment we're in and discuss those
so business has changed a lot do we even
have access to the business you know a
business a restaurant may be closed and
there may be a loss there's a water loss
that occurred you know or fire loss or
whatever it may be we might not have
access to that and the insured may not
want to come out and meet us I had a
water loss when this began in a dentist
office on the first floor and above it
was a doctor's office I had to
coordinate with two individuals to make
sure I could gain access to two
businesses the doctor's office was not
closed and we're going to discuss that a
little bit as it in regards to evidence
because it was an operating doctor's
office with patients coming in and now
we have to conduct an inspection
you know enormous goes into that and in
these Cova days so business the biggest
thing was gaining access residential it
was the parties are still present in the
house discussing everything so PPE is
obviously very important you know I
mentioned up front with the residential
we need to discuss PPE that
needs to be done on every exam every
exam needs to be discussed what we will
be wearing what the minimum is should
parties want to go with a greater level
of PPE I don't think anybody is gonna
mind but it needs to be discussed hey at
this exam all parties are gonna wear
this and for the majority we see in 95
masks gloves we see social distancing I
was at a large exam the last three days
and after everybody would come out you
would see everybody go their own ways in
social distance when we spoke it's very
difficult in an n95 mask to you know I I
was in charge of this exam with 22
people there it's very difficult to give
them a briefing I had to step back 10
feet take my mask off and be very loud
you know ask everybody if they're ok
with that there's a lot of logistics as
to how PPE affects these exams so we're
mostly seeing respirators gloves and 95
masks and at times Tyvek the other thing
we saw with scene inspections is they're
taking longer so understand it may take
longer for your expert to even get to a
scene exam now flights are canceled
right off the bat flights are limited we
now have where let's say you may fly to
a city direct to go to an exam you may
now see a connection some experts are
saying this used to be a 4-hour flight
it's now 6 I can drive it in five or I
can drive it in six so we're seeing a
slowdown you know realize you're experts
it may take them longer to get there the
exams are taking longer this is going to
continue preak ovid many a time whatever
type of loss I recall being shoulder to
shoulder with experts in a crawl space
examining some component of a loss
doesn't happen anymore and it might not
happen again
I don't know what's going to happen but
you have to realize social distancing
continues on a scene exam
good example that comes to mind is a
colleagues of mine were out on a large
loss in the Midwest the loss was so
large and the people there were so many
participants they had to break down how
many went into loss at a time and
literally they were sending five into
the area of origin with the radio giving
them
specified amount of time and then
radioing them out and then they go and
sit and five more go in pre kovat
fifteen twenty people would have been in
there looking at it that exam went from
two days to four days not anybody's
fault
nobody's intentionally expanding the
exam it is where we are so the biggest
thing is expect the scenes to take
longer travel and exams and lastly
evidence has changed the collection of
evidence perfect example is the doctor's
office you know if I am going to remove
evidence from a doctor's office in
today's environment I'm going to need to
go above and beyond to make sure how I
remove that evidence and I'm going to go
above and beyond as to how I store it I
need to consider new factors also there
was a time when I would just sit down
with an insured and they may hand me a
manual for a dryer and I would take that
or receipt can't do that anymore
I've got to use gloves I've got to put
it in bags so evidence collection needs
to be discussed evidence collection
needs to change and I envision that will
change in the future as well
so trip houses impacted laboratory exams
so elaborate lab exams when this all
began almost all of them were just
immediately postponed with no date set
you had all these lab exams on the books
and the labs came back and said
obviously we're just gonna stop we don't
know what's gonna happen I think when
everybody began this process they had no
idea how long it was gonna last I'm sure
many thought a few weeks maybe some
thought much longer but those exams for
the most part are still postponed we are
seeing now rescheduling occurring and
what I was expressing to my clients
about three weeks into it when we
realized this was going to go on for a
long time is we need to get them on the
books now because what we are going to
encounter is everybody trying to get
these lab exams and to be honest it is
what we are encountering now at least in
my section of the country trying to get
all these lab exams scheduled and you're
gonna have so many experts that are
conflicting dates because they are let's
say an expert during this process had 15
lab exams cancel that expert was busy
let's say four or five days a week
pre kovat well now there are four or
five days a week and you're expecting
them to fit in
fifteen additional lab exams with travel
in the next three months not going to
happen it's going to log jam up to the
point where it's going to slow
everything down in terms of scheduling
exams need to get on the books I would
highly recommend anybody listening to
this to please if you have pending exams
get a date set I enter the point where
I'm seeing exam scheduled to August and
that's not due to not being able to
travel that's due to six emails going
through where I can't make that date I
can't make it that date so please get
the exams on the book we've seen
technology request change we have seen
in lab exams some labs have said we're
gonna go forward we will offer some type
of virtual zoom whatever it may be
whatever platform where you can view the
exam those are very specific to certain
types of exams you know if you are maybe
taking a component in to get SEM or EDS
scanned you could zoom that you know
people can share that obviously if
you're breaking down an appliance that
can't be too easily zoomed but we have
seen a requests for we can zoom this a
lot needs to go into that you need to
speak with all parties involved to let
them know we will be live recording we
will be telling you when we were
recording you have to discuss if audio
is gonna be on everybody has to be aware
any comment they make is now on a
recorded line that is gonna be
distributed to all parties so that just
like PPE needs to be discussed and
lastly with lab exams we are still
dealing with travel issues so please
understand you know you can get them on
the books you need to discuss are you
travelling now can you travel and
parties need to understand the travel is
still going to be slowed down and what I
mean by that is I may be available June
9th
however I'm not available June 8th and
now due to limited flights connections I
need a day of travel as well so that's
going to slow the process down for lab
exams as well trip what will the future
look like in forensic engineering and
claims handling so I think the immediate
future is the scheduling issues and
delays slower exams and PPE so I think
the scheduling issues I already
mentioned are going to continue
throughout the year you know exams are
gonna get pushed back back back back
we're gonna add all these exams that
were either held as a one I mentioned
with the infant in July
or all these lab exams and experts
simply are not going to have the time to
fit it all in there and the lab exams I
know I I don't want to harp on that but
those are the worst because you've got
multiple experts trying to find a date
that work so I would expect people to
see scheduling issues through their
remainder of the year at a minimum PPE
is going to change many times on exams
people wouldn't wear PPE and and not
steel boots but in terms of respirators
or whatever it is unless it was you know
a very contaminated exam as fast it's
very dirty exam or whatever maybe the
environment I think you're gonna see
more PPE on a regular basis and I think
you're still gonna see that slow down in
the exam that I mentioned earlier you're
still gonna see maybe a one day exam
bleeding into two because we are
socially distancing while completing the
exam and most importantly I know I've
kind of talked here in this brief
recording about all of our limitations
and what everybody is going through
everybody has to understand that does
not mean it is an excuse not to comply
with current guidelines and standards
while we are still doing this however we
are doing it whether it's through a zoom
whether it is through an expert that may
not be preferred everybody must still
comply with an FPA ASTM and all other
standards that are out there to conduct
an investigation as it should be
conducted Tripp thank you so much for
joining us today thank you very much for
having me that was Tripp Wagner from
expert service provider Jensen Hughes
with services worldwide
and special thanks to today's producer
Frank Bullwinkle thank you all for
joining us for best insurance law
podcast to subscribe to this audio
program go to our webpage wwas concise
plains resource there any suggestions
for a future topic regarding an
insurance law case or issue please email
us at law podcast at AMS comm I'm John
Juba and that was message
best insurance professional resources
features valuable insurance industry
content including searchable profiles of
client recommended insurance attorneys
adjusters and expert service providers
brought to you by a.m. best known
worldwide is a respected source of
insurance industry news and information
visit am best calm / claims resource
[Music]